Curriculum Vitae

June 10, 2017

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science Aug 2008 – May 2011 Purdue University, USA

Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 – May 2008

PSG College of Technology Anna University, India

Experience

Research Fellow, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851 Oct 2015 - present

Research Fellow, Darwin College, Cambridge Oct 2015 - present

Research Associate, University of Cambridge Dec 2014 - present

Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Technical director of OCaml Labs leading the development of Multicore OCaml project. Applying programming languages and program verifcation to solve extreme-scale parallelism and distribution.

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014 Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, USA Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Aug 2012 - Dec 2012 Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) *Aug 2011 – Dec 2011*

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Feb 2012 - May 2012 Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D)

May 2010 – Aug 2010 Advisor: Daniel Waddington San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language - a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Dec 2007 - Apr 2008

Advisor: Sankar Chnab

Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

J4

J3

C7

C5

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell

Jun 2016

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones Journal of Functional Programming (JFP)

Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventu-

Mar 2016

ally Consistent Key-Value Stores

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin, 39(1): 52 64, March 2016

MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML

Nov 2014

J2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 - 674

Efficient Sessions Feb 2013

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster J1 Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 – 167 Invited paper

Conference Publications

DaLi: Database as a Library

May 2017

Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Thomas Gazagnaire, Anil Madhavapeddy, Suresh Jagannathan C8 The 2nd Summit on Advances in Programming Languages (SNAPL)

Oral Presentation

Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores

Jun 2015

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony

Jan 2014

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C6 Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL)

A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC

Nov 2012

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC)

Best paper award

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

Jun 2012

C4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM)

Composable Asynchronous Events

Jun 2011

C3 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan

International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

| C2 | Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION) | June 2010 | |
|---------------------------------------|---|-----------|--|
| C1 | Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP) | Sep 2009 | |
| ❖ Workshop Publications | | | |
| W8 | Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop | Sep 2016 | |
| W7 | Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop | Sep 2016 | |
| W6 | Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop | Sep 2016 | |
| W5 | Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop | Sep 2015 | |
| W4 | Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop | Sep 2013 | |
| W3 | Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA) | Apr 2011 | |
| W2 | The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop | Sep 2010 | |
| W1 | Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP) | Jan 2010 | |
| ❖ Technical Reports and Drafts | | | |
| T1 | Featherweight Threads for Communication KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018 | Nov 2011 | |
| ❖ Teaching/Advising | | | |
| | Cuest Lectures: | | |

- Guest Lectures:
 - Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent 2015–16.
 - Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas 2015–16.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
 - Databases, Lent 2016–17.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2016–17.

- Databases, Michaelmas 2016–17.
- Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2016–17.
- Algorithms, Lent 2015–16.
- Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2015–16.
- Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University

Concurrent and Multicore OCaml: A deep dive

Facebook Tech Talk

- Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
- Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:
 - Nicolas Assouad, ENS Paris, Hardware Support for Composable Lock-free Transactions, Mar 2017 present.
 - Matt Harrison, University of Cambridge, Secure Decentralized Apps, Sep 2016 present.
 - Maxime Lesourd, ENS de Lyon, Verified CPS translation of handlers, Sep 2016 Mar 2017.
 - Philip Dexter, Binghampton University, Approximate computing for OCaml, May 2016 Aug 2016.
 - James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Theo Laurent, ENS, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
 - Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

Talks

| laiks | |
|--|--|
| Composable lock-free programming for Multicore OCaml ABCD Meeting | Nov 2016 University of Edinburgh |
| Practical Algebraic Effect Handlers in Multicore OCaml LFCS Seminar | Nov 2016 University of Edinburgh |
| Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar | Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Madras |
| Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar | Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay |
| Effective parallelism with Reagents Facebook Faculty Summit | Sep 2016 London, UK |
| Multicore OCaml and Programming with Reagents LDN Functionals | Aug 2016 Jane Street UK, London |
| Effect handlers in Multicore OCaml Dagstuhl Seminar | Mar 2016 Dagstuhl, Germany |
| Arrows and Reagents Invited Lecture, Advanced Functional Programming | <i>Mar 2016</i> Cambridge, UK |
| | |

OCaml Platform: Update
OCaml Consortium Meeting

Multicore OCaml: Update
OCaml Developer's Meeting

Nov 2015
Paris, France

Nov 2015
Paris, France

Jan 2016

Menlo Park, CA

Silence is Golden: Controlling Communication and Coordination in Distributed Databases

Darwin College Science Seminar

Oct 2015
Cambridge, UK

Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects

OCaml Workshop 2015

Sep 2015 Vancouver, Canada

Quelea: Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores

Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge

Apr 2015 Cambridge, UK

Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

PhD Defense

Dec 2014
Purdue University

Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming

Invited Lecture

Mar 2014
Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony

PADL 2014

Jan 2014 San Diego, CA

Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud

ML Workshop 2013

Sep 2013 Boston, MA

A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC

MARC 2012

Nov 2012 RWTH Aachen

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

ISMM 2012, Beijing Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge Jun 2012 May 2012

Lightweight Concurrency in GHC

Wrestling Wednesdays

May 2012
Microsoft Research, Cambridge
Jun 2012

Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction

COORDINATION 2012

CWI Amsterdam

Service

- Program Committee member: PMLDC@ECOOP 2017, Off-the-beaten track (OBT) 2017, OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: ECOOP, TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.
- Organizer for Darwin College Science Seminar Series, Oct 2015 present.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.